{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This politician wrote the My Day column to advocate for civil rights and helped create a planned community in Arthurdale to provide homes for disenfranchised miners. This probable lover of Lorena Hickok employed social secretary Lucy Mercer, who indirectly inspired this woman to broaden her social life by having an affair with her husband. The UN Commission on Human Rights was chaired by, for ten points, what American social reformer, the wife of the 32nd President?",
      "answer": "Anna Eleanor Roosevelt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Jean Calas was accused of murdering his son to prevent him from performing this action and was defended by Voltaire in his Treatise on Toleration. Gabrielle d’Estr´ees supported a royal performance of this action in 1593. Spanish Moors who performed this action were called moriscos. For ten points, name this action that was performed by Henry IV upon winning the French Wars of Religion, supposedly declaring “Paris is well worth a Mass.”",
      "answer": [
        "converting to Catholicism",
        "word forms and equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this conflict, a leader’s plans were almost derailed by a charge led by Baldwin de Carron and Garnier de Nablus. Forces captured the Sultanate of Rum’s capital during this conflict’s Battle of Iconium. Prior to this campaign, Guy of Lusignan was captured at the Battle of Hattin. After the Battle of Arsuf in this crusade, an invasion failed to take Jerusalem. Christians were allowed access to holy places in Jerusalem as a result of, for ten points, what crusade against Saladin led by Richard the Lionheart?",
      "answer": "Third Crusade ”Crusade” not needed after mentioned"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city was the headquarters of Ryan Airlines, who constructed The Spirit of St. Louis for Charles Lindbergh. In 2016, a twenty-five year legal fight was resolved regarding the placing of a cross on government land at this city’s Mount Soledad. This city’s Point Loma serves as a naval base for the Pacific Fleet, and its Balboa Park contains a zoo that pioneered open-air exhibits. For ten points, name this California city whose San Ysidro district is home to a large border crossing to Tijuana, Mexico.",
      "answer": "San Diego"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the Missouri River, Bloody Island gained its nickname for being the location of many of these events. James Shields and Abraham Lincoln almost participated in one of these events, another of which involved future president Andrew Jackson and led to the death of Charles Dickinson. Weehawken, New Jersey hosted several of these events, including one that killed a former Secretary of the Treasury in 1804. For ten points, name this type of incident in which Aaron Burr shot and killed Alexander Hamilton.",
      "answer": "duels"
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician attracted controversy and massive protests for his murder of the activist Hugo Spadafora and his alleged role in the death of his predecessor, Omar Torrijos. After this man claimed sanctuary in a Catholic church, Navy SEALs blasted rock music outside the compound for three days of psychological warfare. Operation Just Cause targeted this man’s country, despited his previous service as a CIA ally in the War on Drugs. For ten points, name this former leader of Panama who was deposed in 1989.",
      "answer": "Manuel Antonio Noriega Moreno"
    },
    {
      "question": "Sofonisba Anguissola painted a young girl raising her left arm while playing this game with her sisters. Several versions of the Shahnama illustrate the story of Burzhmir’s introduction of this game to Iran from India. A set of equipment for playing this game thought to be made in Trondheim was found in 1831 in the Hebrides on the island of Lewis; that set of ivory figurines uses red and white, rather than the traditional black and white. For ten points, name this game played with rooks, bishops and queens.",
      "answer": "chess"
    },
    {
      "question": "This woman gained power after a monarch attempted to bypass the Third Succession Act. This great-grandaughter of Henry VII was implicated in Wyatt’s Rebellion, despite only her father actually taking part in it. This woman awaited coronation for a year in the Tower of London, but her followers quickly abandoned her in support of Mary I, who had her executed shortly after being crowned. For ten points, name this woman who was Queen of England for nine days.",
      "answer": [
        "Lady Jane Grey",
        "Lady Jane Dudley"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This election year involved the first instance of a man in a chicken suit harassing a candidate; that instance occurred outside the Detroit Economic Club after that incumbent refused to debate his opponents. During this election, James Carville helped associate one candidate with the phrase “It’s the economy, stupid.” During this election, a third-party candidate claimed a “giant sucking sound” would result from NAFTA. For ten points, name this election year in which Ross Perot and incumbent George H. W. Bush lost to Bill Clinton.",
      "answer": "U.S. Presidential Election of 1992"
    },
    {
      "question": "During a voyage from Madagascar, the pirate John Thurber gave Henry Woodward this crop, which Woodward turned into a major crop in North America. The Engelberg Huller and Winnowing Barns processed this crop. Thomas Jefferson investigated why an Italian variety of this crop was more expensive than the “Carolina Gold” variety, which was grown near the Ashley and Combahee Rivers in tidal zones. The Banaue [ban-ow-ay] terraces in the Philippines were created to grow, for ten points, what food crop?",
      "answer": "rice"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2005, this man was dismissed as Deputy President after his friend, Schabir Shaik, was convicted on fraud and corruption charges. This former communist recently faced impeachment after the case Economic Freedom Fighters v. Speaker of the National Assembly ruled that he had siphoned funds meant to upgrade the Nkandla house. During this man’s 2005 rape trial, he claimed that he took a shower to prevent himself from contracting HIV. Improper ties to the Gupta family helped bring down, for ten points, what former President of South Africa?",
        "answer": "Jacob Zuma"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This former President of South Africa ordered Deputy President Zuma’s 2005 dismissal. He himself resigned as President in 2008.",
        "answer": "Thabo Mbeki"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Salmon P. Chase served six years in the Senate as a member of this political party. As a senator from New Hampshire, a presidential candidate of this party led the drive to abolish flogging in the Navy. This party, whose final presidential nominee was John P. Hale, emerged when the Barnburners withdrew their support from Lewis Cass, instead nominating Martin Van Buren for the presidency. For ten points, name this anti-slavery party tht was active from 1848 until its absorption by the Republican Party.",
        "answer": "Free Soil Party"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1848, the Free Soil’s vice-presidential nominee was Charles Francis, a son of a former president and a member of this political family.",
        "answer": [
          "Adams family",
          "Charles Francis Adams"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city essentially boycotted The Sun newspaper for spreading false allegations about the Hillsborough disaster, in which 95 fans of a team from this city died in a crush during an FA Cup semifinal. The Quarrymen began playing in this city’s Cavern Club in 1957. This city’s two largest soccer clubs, Everton and a club whose anthem is “You’ll Never Walk Alone,” play the Merseyside Derby. Anfield is the home of “the Reds” in, for ten points, what English industrial port city, the home city of the Beatles?",
        "answer": "Liverpool"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Liverpool’s Anfield is one of many English stadiums to have a grandstand named Spion Kop, in reference to a 1900 battle in this war.",
        "answer": "Second Anglo-Boer War"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man allegedly dismembered Marcus Marius Gratidianus and paraded his head around the streets of Rome. Gaius Cethegus and Lentulus Sura were accomplices to this man in his most famous action, which was chronicled by Sallust. This man used the promise of cancellation of debts to recruit veterans to his cause, which grew out of resentment toward his loss of the 64 BC consular election. Four orations were made against this man by Cicero, this man’s rival and target. For ten points, name this Roman who led a failed conspiracy against the Roman Republic.",
        "answer": "Catiline or Lucius Sergius Catilina"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In response to Cicero’s oration, Catiline stormed out of the Senate in a huff, falsely claiming to go into exile in Massalia. Today, the ancient city of Massalia is this modern city on the Mediterranean coast.",
        "answer": "Marseilles"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire was led by a ruler who re-conquered Red Ruthenia and made peace with Casimir the Restorer. The Pechenegs launched numerous raids into this empire and besieged its capital city in 968. After it was invaded by Batu Khan, this empire was put under the so-called “Tatar Yoke.” A grand prince who ruled this empire employed the Varangians to reconquer Novgorod in 978. Figures like Yaroslav the Wise ruled, for ten points, what ancient Russian federation of the Middle Ages, based in modern Ukraine?",
        "answer": "Kievan Rus’"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Kievan Rus’ and its successor state, the Grand Duchy of Moscow, were ruled by leaders from this dynasty, named after its Viking founder. This dynasty preceded the Romanovs as rulers of Russia.",
        "answer": [
          "Rurik dynasty",
          "Rurikids"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man sent Crist´obal de Olid to conquer Honduras, but later sent two warships after him when he declared independence. After landing at Veracruz, this man scuttled his own ships to prevent his men from retreating. This man had a son with his interpreter, La Malinche, who was one of the first mestizos. This man’s only surviving documents, the Cartas de Relaci´on, describe how he was mistaken for a feathered serpent god. For ten points, name this Spanish conquistador who conquered the Aztec empire.",
        "answer": "Hern´an Cort´es"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Cort´es claim that he was mistaken for Quetzalcoatl is found in a letter to this Spanish king, who funded his expedition.",
        "answer": "Charles I of Spain or Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician advocated for an end to apartheid in the “Day of Affirmation” Speech, and he wrote about his experiences serving as chief counsel for the McClellan Committee and feuding with Teamsters boss Jimmy Hoffa in his book The Enemy Within. Shortly after a meeting with Cesar Chavez, this man announced his campaign to run for President, but after winning the 1968 California primary, he was assassinated. For ten points, name this politician who served as Attorney General under his brother, John.",
        "answer": [
          "Robert Francis Kennedy",
          "RFK",
          "Bobby Kennedy"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man, partially motivated by anti-Israeli sentiment, murdered Robert Kennedy in 1968.",
        "answer": "Sirhan Sirhan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A documentary of “scorched earth techniques in China” inspired the first movement of a piece that this composer dubbed his “war symphony.” This composer, whose Symphony in Three Movements was choreographed by George Balanchine, wrote the latter half of his neoclassical Symphony in C after fleeing Paris in 1939. This man wrote a ballet in which Kaschei the Immortal is defeated when Prince Ivan destroys a magic egg. For ten points, name this Russian-born modernist composer of The Firebird who caused a Parisian riot with The Rite of Spring.",
        "answer": "Igor Stravinsky"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Firebird was the first of Stravinsky’s collaborations with what impresario, who founded the Ballets Russes [“ballet” roose] and also produced The Rite of Spring?",
        "answer": "Sergei Diaghilev"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "American Political Labels",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Three-word phrase often abbreviated to refer to the Republican Party.",
          "answer": "Grand Old Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "Moniker given to the nativist American Party because its members professed ignorance of it when asked.",
          "answer": "“Know-Nothings”"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for a northerner who moved to the South to exploit the post-Civil War economy.",
          "answer": "carpetbaggers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term that described a Southerner who collaborated with the Republican Reconstruction.",
          "answer": "scalawags"
        },
        {
          "question": "Civil War currency that lent its name to a populist political party.",
          "answer": "Greenback Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for Republican defectors who supported Grover Cleveland over James G. Blaine in 1884.",
          "answer": "mugwumps"
        },
        {
          "question": "Republican faction that opposed the Stalwarts during the 1880s.",
          "answer": "Half-Breeds"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pejorative phrase used to describe clubs of anti-corruption activists during the Gilded Age.",
          "answer": "“Goo-goos” or good government guys"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Memorials for the World Wars",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Battleship sunk at Pearl Harbor whose wreck was memorialized.",
          "answer": "USS Arizona"
        },
        {
          "question": "American battleship where the Japanese instrument of surrender was signed, now a museum in Pearl Harbor.",
          "answer": "USS Missouri"
        },
        {
          "question": "World War II battle memorialized by the statue The Motherland Calls on Mamayev Kurgan.",
          "answer": "Battle of Stalingrad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Red flower whose remembrance type is often worn in November in the Commonwealth.",
          "answer": "poppy"
        },
        {
          "question": "City whose Museum of Science and Industry was left in ruins in what is now Peace Memorial Park.",
          "answer": "Hiroshima"
        },
        {
          "question": "Holiday held on April 25th to commemorate a pair of national forces that fought at Gallipoli.",
          "answer": "Anzac Day"
        },
        {
          "question": "Articles of clothing left by Arrow Cross victims near the Danube in Budapest.",
          "answer": [
            "shoes",
            "anything related to footwear"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Small raised brass plates set outside of the former houses of Jews who died in the Holocaust.",
          "answer": "stumbling stones or stolpersteine"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Wars of Alexander the Great",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire led from Persepolis that he conquered in 330 BC.",
          "answer": "Persian Empire or Achaemenid Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom in the north of Greece ruled by Alexander and his father.",
          "answer": "Macedonia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Father of Alexander. He was assassinated in 336 BC.",
          "answer": "Philip II of Macedon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Phoenician city that he besieged for seven months in 332 BC and captured by building a causeway.",
          "answer": "Tyre"
        },
        {
          "question": "331 battle in Iraq, often considered his greatest victory, after which Bessus murdered Darius III.",
          "answer": "Battle of Gaugamela"
        },
        {
          "question": "334 battle where he defeated Memnon of Rhodes and was saved by his friend Cleitus the Black.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Granicus River"
        },
        {
          "question": "326 battle where he defeated King Porus to gain control of the Punjab.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Hydaspes River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fortress near Samarkand captured in 327 by Alexander, where he first met his wife Roxana.",
          "answer": "Sogdian Rock or Rock of Ariamazes"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In response to a rebellion led by the Senussi Order, this man ordered the genocidal “pacification” of another country. In a confrontation with Greece, this leader sent troops to bombard and occupy the island of (20 pts)",
        "Corfu. This leader formed the one-time Stresa Front with his counterparts, Pierre Laval and Ramsay MacDonald; the Front broke apart after this man declared war against (10 pts)",
        "Haile Selassie [“highly” sel-ah-see]. This man rose to power when a march by his Blackshirt paramilitaries forced the hand of Victor Emmanuel III. For ten points, name this fascist Italian dictator."
      ],
      "answer": "Benito Amilcare Andrea Mussolini"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Friedrich Wohler reacted cyanogen [sigh-an-oh-jen] with this compound to produce oxalic acid in what may have been the first organic synthesis. In another synthesis also developed by Wohler, lead cyanate and this compound can be used to produce (20 pts)",
        "urea. A synthesis of this compound was necessary for Germany to overcome the Allied blockade of Chilean (10 pts)",
        "saltpeter; that synthesis can also be used to produce fertilizer and uses hydrogen and nitrogen as its reactants. The Haber-Bosch process creates, for ten points, what compound with chemical formula NH ? 3"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "ammonia",
        "NH before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man piloted the MiG Mad Marine. In the Savings and Loans scandal, this man and John McCain were the only members of the Keating Five to be acquitted. The first (20 pts)",
        "panorama photo of the United States was taken in an aircraft piloted by this man. This senator from Ohio flew in the Discovery in 1998, becoming the (10 pts)",
        "oldest man in space. As pilot of the Friendship Seven, this man made three orbits of Earth in 1962. For ten points, name this member of the Mercury Seven, the first American astronaut to orbit the Earth."
      ],
      "answer": "John Glenn"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A relief by Pietro Lombardo showing a man reading at a lectern is found in one of these locations that is controversially in Ravenna instead of in Florence. Petrarch planted a tree at one of these locations in the entrance to a (20 pts)",
        "tunnel in Naples. A glass wall was built around one of these locations designed by Jacob Epstein to curtail the tradition of visitors putting on lipstick and kissing a stone sculpture of a sphinx. (10 pts)",
        "Poet’s Corner of Westminster Abbey is home to several of, for ten points, what historic sites that sometimes do not actually contain the remains of people like Dante, Virgil, or Oscar Wilde?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "tombs of authors",
        "equivalents related to burial sites, graves, etc. of authors",
        "Dante’s Tomb, Virgil’s Tomb starting at the second sentence,",
        "Oscar Wilde’s Tomb starting at the third sentence"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Louis Menand’s “The Metaphysical Club” discusses the birth of this intellectual school from a conversational club founded by Oliver Wendell Holmes Jr. The namesake “maxim” of this school argues that the conception of an idea is only made up of its (20 pts)",
        "effects. Charles Sanders Peirce is known as the “father” of this school, whose most famous proponent argued for it as a (10 pts)",
        "“New Name for Some Old Ways of Thinking.” For ten points, name this American school of philosophy that focused on the practical consequences of ideas."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "pragmatism",
        "word forms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A tune in which each of the thirteen parts covers a month of this event includes the line “the river flowing and barley growing, what do we suffer for?” This event was preceded by several defeats for Otto Braun in a series of Encirclement Campaigns. The (20 pts)",
        "Zunyi Conference strengthened the position of a key figure in this event, which succeeded partly because warlords did not interfere. (10 pts)",
        "Propaganda posters after this event told citizens to remember the soldiers who engaged in this event “if [they] feel tired.” The Kuomintang chased the People’s Liberation’s Army during, for ten points, what storied retreat led by Mao Zedong?"
      ],
      "answer": "Long March or Changzheng"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In response to locals refusing to collect taxes, this ruler declared that “the public order entirely emanates from me” in the “Flagellation” speech. This ruler supported Pope Clement XI’s bull Unigenitus, which led to the Jansenist Controversy. This ruler’s marriage to (20 pts)",
        "Marie Leszczynska [lesh-CHEEN-ska] was a factor in his backing of her father, Stanislaw I, in the War of Polish Succession. This ruler lost the colony of (10 pts)",
        "New France in the North American theatre of the Seven Years’ War and his unpopular string of mistresses included Madame du Barry and Madame de Pompadour. For ten points, name this great-grandson and successor of Louis XIV."
      ],
      "answer": "Louis XV of France"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The third wave of these items were marketed with a poster showing the caption “Over the top for you.” Mary Pickford started a nationwide speaking campaign to sell these items, which were advertised by a division of the (20 pts)",
        "Creel Committee. During the drive to sell the fifth wave of these, medallions representing them were created by the (10 pts)",
        "Treasury Department using metal melted from German cannons. Over $17 billion dollars were raised by the sale of, for ten points, what loans used to fund the Allies during World War I?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "liberty bonds",
        "liberty loans",
        "Victory Loans",
        "war bonds"
      ]
    }
  ]
}